What if you could improve your arthritis
pain without having to change your diet,
but still mimicking an arthritis
improving diet? There's some evidence
that a low carbohydrate diets,
especially those that increase ketones,
a molecule produced by your liver, can
improve arthritis. But adopting a very
low carbohydrate diet that raises
ketones enough, is tough for some.
That's because the lower your
carbohydrate intake, the greater your
ketone levels generally. Fortunately,
there's an easy solution. Let's get into
it. The believed reason for why the
ketogenic diet leads to arthritis
benefits is because of these
aforementioned ketones. They're
molecules that your liver produces when
there's insufficient carbohydrate or
glucose entering the liver. It's an
alternate fuel source for many of your
cells. And yet, more research indicates
that they can be more than just
nutrients to your cells. In this case,
arthritis. Ketones reduce the production
of inflammatory molecules from your
cells which is especially powerful in
rheumatoid arthritis which is
characterized primarily by increased
inflammation in the body leading to the
destruction of the joint structure in
the body by the immune cells. Reducing
inflammation means reducing these
activated destructive cells and
alleviating the insult to the joint
structure. Since ketones reduce the
expression of certain inflammatory
molecules like cytoines, interrucan 1
beta, interlucan 6, interlucan 18 that
activate these immune cells, it makes
sense to focus on the ketones. There's a
ton on the mechanisms that I'll cover in
more detail in other content, but
generally this is the thought process
for why a ketogenic diet that encourages
ketone production would have this
beneficial arthritis effect. Still, like
we discussed before, it's not feasible
for everyone. And even if it is,
wouldn't it be nice to ensure your
ketone levels stay elevated, even if you
were to accidentally slip and fall and
your mouth lands on a cookie and
accidentally chew it multiple times
before swallowing it? Happens all the
time. The National Bureau of BS
Statistics indicates it happens 100% in
certain households. So, this isn't
theoretical. Okay. How do we pick our
cookie and eat it too? By accident, of
course. That's where this study comes
in. The researchers randomly assigned
men and women with rheumatoid arthritis
to consume their usual diet, but
supplement with a mediumchain
triglyceride supplement or a longchain
triglyceride supplement. I'll explain
what those are in a second. And
participants were instructed to consume
each supplement every day for 16 weeks
with a major caveat that we'll get into.
The mediumchain triglycerides and
longchain triglycerides are simply
differentized fat molecules. One
contains 6 to 12 carbons linked together
and the other contains 13 to 21 carbons.
I'll let you figure out which is which.
MCTs or mediumchain triglycerides are
more easily absorbed by the liver and
can therefore be easily converted to
ketones. LCTs or longchain triglycerides
are not as readily converted. So you can
imagine that the MCT group experienced
an increase in ketones, right? The
answer is yes. As seen here, the control
or longchain triglyceride consuming
group is on the left and the MCT or
mediumchain triglyceride group is on the
right for the test group. The T0 is the
baseline before the supplementation. The
T2 is 8 weeks later and T4 is 16 weeks
later. According to the statistics on
the right side, since the P values fall
below 0.05, 05. There's an identified
difference between the two groups with
the test group having at least double
the ketones in the blood. Okay, good.
Supplementation worked. The next
question should be what happened to
these people's arthritis? Well, for that
the researchers used an SDAI or
simplified disease activity index to
identify disease severity based on a
number of criteria for tender joints,
swollen joints through a physician
assessment and much more. If values go
up, that indicates worse symptom
severity. But for this next graph only,
ignore that. If the bar goes up, that's
a good change or an inverse change.
Here's the measure of change. There's a
statistically significant change in the
test group. So the MCT supplementing
group. In that case, there's a positive
effect as in the improvements in
arthritis symptoms. So pretty sweet. the
test condition shows improvements.
Except that these data are quite
misleading. And this is one of those
instances where I disagree with the
researchers. And this is where that
major caveat comes into play. I just
showed you the total change over the 16
weeks. But here's the kicker. While yes,
everyone in the MCT group did consume
MCTs throughout the 16 weeks, at the
8week mark, they started to
co-supplement fiber. So the first eight
weeks MCT or LCT only and the final 8
weeks MCT or LCT plus fiber. So now the
question is was it the MCTs or the fiber
intake that led to these improvements?
Fortunately we have the data to tease
that out at least well for the most
part. For that we can look at this chart
again we see the SDI scale with the
three time points. Remember T2 is MCT or
LCT only and T4 is including fiber. Now
if we compare the broken up by the
exposure of MCT in isolation or with
fiber, we see no difference in the first
8 weeks when MCT was alone. However, we
do detect a difference once fiber is
added to the mix indicating by a
statistically significant result at the
T4 measure there. Now naturally your
first inclination is to think well then
it must be the fiber and that's a
reasonable next step but we have
evidence that indicates otherwise.
Remember the control group also consume
the same fiber and they did not
experience these benefits. So the proper
conclusion should be that the fiber plus
MCTs in co- combination yields these
effects that or it takes longer than 8
weeks for the MCT to exert its
beneficial effects. As always, there's
more to the story here that we'll get to
next. The reality is that there's much
more to cover here, including the types
of fiber, dosing strategies, and other
effective anti- rheumatoid arthritis
molecules that could also play a factor.
I'm covering all that in my full
analysis found in the Physionic Insiders
along with access to all my other
research, more applicable takeaways, a
monthly podcast that distills all of
this nicely into one place, a premium
email list that delivers all the work to
your doorstep, uh live sessions with me
to discuss more deeply, and much more.
If you're interested, check out the
Physionic Insiders. The link is in the
description box. Okay. Interestingly,
CRP levels, a general metric of
inflammation, along with another
arthritis measure, did not improve. That
might be because there weren't enough
people in the study for these outcomes
because they're known as secondary
outcomes. And studies are usually more
concerned with their primary outcome,
which is what we just covered. Still, I
found the researchers conclusions
incorrect in two ways. One, they
mentioned that other studies on fiber
have not shown improvements in
arthritis. But if you open the studies,
which I did, the studies clearly show
improvements in arthritis symptoms,
although there's no placebo group in the
in that cited study. Either way, it's
incorrect to then say that fiber has no
effect. Two, the researchers conclusions
center around mediumchain triglycerides
and not around fiber. They even state
that MCTs alone lead to improvements
which is as we pointantly went over not
true. In addition, they did some
correlation analyses which means that
they tried to find a simple association
between different changing variables in
the study. So I'll show you the data but
we don't need to actually go through it
because it doesn't tell us much. But it
does speak to a bit of bias by the
researchers I think. Here we go. I know
this is a lot. The main point here is
that they are relating our arthritis
test the SDAI to BHB or beta
hydroxybutyrate. So that's the ketone
levels. And we can see that while there
is a relationship, the relationship is
considered weak. In fact, everything
else CRP and VAS, which is this uh other
arthritis test, have stronger
relationships with it. So this uh focus
on the MCTs seems kind of nonsensical to
me. Not to mention that they didn't
report the relationship of fiber to the
same arthritis test. It might have shown
a stronger relationship. So, it's
definitely possible that the conflicts
of interest led to this reduced emphasis
on fiber and greater emphasis on MCTs
since the researchers work for a food
company. Funny enough, that food company
sells MCTs and fiber. So, you'd think
that they'd be
ambivalent. Whatever. The point being I
disagree with their conclusions. So what
are the takeaways here? The takeaway
here is that this study indicated
mediumchain triglycerides
supplementation co-supplemented with
fiber improves rheumatoid arthritis
symptoms without any changes to diet. In
fact, the effect is pretty significant.
about a five to six point drop in the
arthritis scale, which is enough to
almost reclassify a person from a more
serious symptoms to more moderate
symptoms, which is really not bad at
all. The thing is, a mediumchain
triglyceride is clearly an effective
way. It's one way of improving arthritis
symptoms, but there's powerful evidence
that I'm even more impressed by in
another supplement right here. I'll see
you over there.